<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Abrahams sute for Sodome a sermon preached at Pauls Cr[o]sse the 25 of August, 1611 / by Robert Milles, preacher of Gedny fenne, and Sutton St. Edmonds in Holland Lincolneshire.</title>
            <author>Milles, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07544</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17924.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4786</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23887164</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23887164</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26950</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07544)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26950)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1837:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Abrahams sute for Sodome a sermon preached at Pauls Cr[o]sse the 25 of August, 1611 / by Robert Milles, preacher of Gedny fenne, and Sutton St. Edmonds in Holland Lincolneshire.</title>
                  <author>Milles, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[108] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Hall for Mathew Lawe and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church yard at the signe of the Foxe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸(-A1) B-F⁸ G⁸ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis XVIII, 32 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26950:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26950:1"/>
            <p>ABRAHAM SVTE FOR SODOME. A Sermon Preached at <hi>Pauls Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe the</hi> 25 <hi>of</hi> AVGVST. 1611. By ROBERT MILLES, Preacher of <hi>Gedny fenne,</hi> and <hi>Sutton S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Edmonds</hi> in Holland <hi>Lincolneſhire</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>William Hall</hi> for <hi>Mathew Lawe,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in Pauls Church yard at the ſigne of the Foxe. 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epistle_dedicatory">
            <pb facs="tcp:26950:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26950:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull Sir WILLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AM WELBY, <hi>Knight of the</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable order of the BATH, felicitie in this life, and ſaluation in the next.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the elect Lady and her childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom he loued in the truth:<note place="margin">2. Ioh. 1.</note> So in ſingleneſſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:26950:3"/>ſame ſpirite (Right Worſhipfull) I conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate vnto you this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall gift and plaine diſcourſe, whi h as an adiutor (rather then an auditor) in my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, you <hi>viua vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce</hi> lately heard deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>Cantare in foro</hi> was a Romaine abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie; and when a man ſpeaketh wiſely but once in his life, hee muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb facs="tcp:26950:3"/>be in Print, <hi>dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it inſipies.</hi> Such ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſpirites are conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>Rachels</hi> at <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> pregnancie:<note place="margin">Gen. 30.</note> Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian flies in Jſraels fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:<note place="margin">Exod. 1.12.</note> muttering <hi>Sauls</hi> at <hi>Dauids</hi> ſucceſſe:<note place="margin">1. Sam 18.8.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull <hi>Amaziahs</hi> at <hi>Amos</hi> induſtrie:<note place="margin">Amos 7.12.</note> and ſuch as, <hi>Cum ſua non edunt, carpunt aliena,</hi> let them either commend or amend, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue
<pb facs="tcp:26950:4"/>or publiſh <hi>meum</hi> or <hi>ſuum.</hi> The Orator ſpake better then theſe men doe, <hi>Omnis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra cura debet in hoc verſari ſemper, ſipoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumus, vt boni ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid efficiamus: ſin minùs, vt certè nihil mali.</hi> All the good J can in this regard is, by <hi>Scire meum, vt ſciat alter,</hi> and for ſiniſter cenſure J anſwere with
<pb facs="tcp:26950:4"/>the Prophet:<note place="margin">Eſay 49.4.</note> My iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is with the Lord, and my worke with my God. Jt is fathered of Saint <hi>Hierome, Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caeſum flagellis ad tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal Dei,</hi> that hee was whipped before Gods ſeate for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant reading of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Authors: and that hee was accuſed there, <hi>quod Cicero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianus, non Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus
<pb facs="tcp:26950:5"/>foret,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee made a vow vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to abiure them.</p>
            <p>And in this age of vanitie, wherein pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane pamphlets are as dainty nouelties, as Apes and Peacockes were in <hi>Salomons</hi> daies from Cilicia:<note place="margin">1. Kin. 10.22</note> what can bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beſeeme Chriſtians, then to reade ſacred Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie, and to meditate in that, which tendeth to
<pb facs="tcp:26950:5"/>edification,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.2.</note> 
               <hi>in eodem prato lepurem, lacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, florem reperias:</hi> &amp; if perhaps cinicall <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> by cumical cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſitie out of <hi>Sampſons</hi> dead Lyon extract poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note place="margin">Iudg. 14.14.</note> yet a well affected Apollos will finde foode and ſweeteneſſe. Sith importunity hath preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with mee among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>ſpectare, &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctari,</hi> I commend this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb facs="tcp:26950:6"/>(Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) to your acceptance and protection, which if you ſhall pleaſe to patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſe now floting like a poore Hollander in an Arke of reede in this Sea of glaſſe,<note place="margin">Apoc. 15.2.</note> and iniuriouſly handled by prophane Philiſtines; <hi>Tu patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eris, quando maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra canemus.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips in all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie duly deuoted,</hi> Robert Milles.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26950:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſute for <hi>Sodome.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GENESIS 18.32.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I will not deſtroy it for tennes ſake.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and bleſſed beloued: <hi>Ignis non melius quam igne, &amp; amor amore accenditur:</hi> As the flame is continued by fire, ſo friendſhip by reciprocall amity, ſaith <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> And this was ſeene and obſerued in GOD himſelfe,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.10.</note> the firſt friend and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of mankinde, towards his
<pb facs="tcp:26950:7"/>ſeruant <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faithfull. For as God did manifeſt his profeſſed loue by manifold promiſes to him, and daily conference with him; So <hi>Abraham</hi> againe repaied God (<hi>lege talionis</hi> as it were) for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall, obedience, ſacrifice, praiſe, and praiers, ſo that both their affections mutually were reuiued and preſerued by ſuch friendly meanes, euen as fire is maintained by fuell. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſundrie ſignes of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour toward <hi>Abraham,</hi> God was neuer more familiar with him then in this Dialogue, and neighbourly parlce, betwixt them two in behalfe of the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites.</hi> For when God pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in his ſecret and ſacred wiſdome to deſtroy the Citie of <hi>Sodome,</hi> (whoſe ſinnes cried
<pb facs="tcp:26950:7"/>for vengeance from heauen) hee firſt after the manner of men pauſed on the matter, and was loath to doe it, before hee had taken the aduiſe of a friend, or before he made <hi>Abraham</hi> (whom the Apoſtle tearmeth Gods friend) priuie to his purpoſe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.23.</note> 
               <hi>Shall I hide from Abraham that which I doe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Heereupon <hi>Abraham</hi> aſſured of Gods loue, began to argue, and to reaſon the caſe with God, and often crauing pardon for his boldneſſe, hee told the Lord, that it ſtood not with his iuſtice and credit (who is high Lord chiefe Iuſtice of the whole world) to deſtroy the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous with the wicked: and there fore deſired him if there could be found fifty good men in the Citie, to ſpare it for their ſake:
<pb facs="tcp:26950:8"/>which God of his mercy, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee alwaies tempereth his iudgements, fauourably gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and eaſily yeelded vnto. <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſtraightway goeth with a priuie ſearch through the Citie of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and at laſt after much labour loſt, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to God with a <hi>non eſt inuentus:</hi> and then after the manner of courtly Petitioners, <hi>Qui timidè rogat, negare docet:</hi> Hee that asketh faintly teacheth how to bee denied flatly, as <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> ſpeaketh. <hi>Abraham</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded further, and ſtill (vnder correction for his preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) hee obtained from God a writte <hi>ad melius inquirendum,</hi> and then hee falleth from fifty to fiue and fortie, then to forty, ſo to thirty, nay, to twenty: and at laſt remembring, that God
<pb facs="tcp:26950:8"/>would not the death of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.23.</note> he vrgeth him with his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and now the ſixt time he praieth the Lord to ſpare <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> if it ſhall affoord but tenne righteous perſons. And in theſe words God ſetteth downe his reſt, and finall reſolution, and bids <hi>Abraham</hi> take it for an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, and ſo content himſelfe: <hi>I will not deſtroy it for tens ſake.</hi> So that my diſcourſe at this time for your fairing (right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, right Worſhipfull, and bleſſed Brethren) may bee called <hi>Abrahams ſute for So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> wherein for methode and memory ſake I will tie my ſelfe to three parties, which ſhall ſtand in ſtead of three parts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in God his ſlowneſſe, in executing iudgement, and puniſhing ſinne.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26950:9"/>
            <p>Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in <hi>Abraham,</hi> the ſympathie, and compaſſion of the godly for their brethren.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in <hi>Sodome,</hi> wherein ten righteous perſons coulde not be found, the ſmall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the faithfull, and fewnes of good men in the Church.</p>
            <p>Among all the names of God in the whole and holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Drut.</hi> 32.6. <hi>Eſay</hi> 63.16. <hi>Malac.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.9. 2. Cor. 6.18. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17.</note> there is one more familiar, comfortable, and delightſome to his children, then all thereſt, and that is the name of Father, which he moſt commonly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſeth in nature. For as affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate fathers, and indulgent parents in correcting their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren giue an admonition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, (rebuke goes before the rod, and a warning before the whipping:) So it pleaſeth our heauenly Father in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:26950:9"/>due puniſhment for our ſinnes, to giue vs a <hi>caueat</hi> before his <hi>capias,</hi> and alwaies to warne vs, before he wound vs.<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Thus did hee deale fatherly with the firſt world, to whom he graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aboue an hundred yeeres, ſpace for repentance, whilſt that <hi>Noah,</hi> (whom the Apoſtle calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauld or Preacher of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) was compoſing the Arke for ſecuritie of the worlds re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</note> Thus dealt God with populous <hi>Niniuie,</hi> and would not ſuffer ſleepy-headed <hi>Ionas</hi> to reſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iona.</hi> 3.1.</note> vntill he had proclaimed his embaſſage in the ſtreetes. Thus did the Meſſiah Chriſt ſhew himſelfe a father to <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37.</note> who would often haue gathered them together, and ſaued them, but they would
<pb facs="tcp:26950:10"/>nor. Yea, thus long did God forbeare the Citie of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and daily forewarned them by rightcous <hi>Lot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7.</note> whoſe ſoule was continually grieued at their vncleanenes, and duly preſaged their ouerthrow. It is memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of <hi>Bias</hi> a Iudge of <hi>Greece,</hi> that he neuer gaue ſentence of death vpon any on the bench but hee ſorrowed, and ſhed teares. And ſuch a tender-har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Iudge is God himſelfe in puniſhing ſinners, as that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing grieueth him more, then to condemne a ſinner, or to caſt away a man by death: which the Prophet conſidering, ſaide, <hi>God puniſheth not with his heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lanent.</hi> 3.32</note> And the Wiſeman laieth forth Gods vnwillingneſſe to correct, as plainely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sapient.</hi> 12.12.</note> 
               <hi>Thou chastneſt them meaſurably that goe wrong, and
<pb facs="tcp:26950:10"/>warneſt them by putting them in rememberance of the thing wherein they haue offended, that leauing wickedneſſe, they may beleeue in thee.</hi> The ſweeteſt leſſon,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.1.</note> that euer <hi>Dauid.</hi> Iſraels ſweet Singer either felt or ſung at any time vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary on his Harpe and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringed inſtrument,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.15.103.8.</note> it was of Gods mercy, all his deſcant was of Gods patience, and the foote and burthen of all his Pſalmes is nothig elſe but of Gods long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="145"/> the kindeneſſe of the Lord:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="136"/> his mercy is ouer all his workes, and the mercy of the Lord endureth for euer.</p>
            <p>Yea, further to ſhew you how loath and vnwilling God is in puniſhing ſinne, the Prophet reſembleth the Lord to an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.12.</note> which bendeth his bow, vnlocketh his quiuer, and rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth
<pb facs="tcp:26950:11"/>beth his ſhafts before hee ſhoot. And to a man of warre, which ſtretcheth himſelfe, flouriſheth with his weapons, trauazeth his ground, and whetteth his ſword before he ſtrike. <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> the Emperour was ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, as that hee alwaies gaue tenne daies liberty to the enemy for deliberation, before hee would ſhew anie extremitie. And as kind a Captaine was he, who in beſieging any City firſt vſed to diſplay a white enſigne, next day a blacke banner, and at laſt (if they would not yeeld) red colours in ſigne of blood, fire and ſword. O Bleſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, and Chriſtian Citizens, farre more pittifull is the Lord of hoaſts towards ſinners, long ſuffering, great in mercy, and repenting for euill,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Icel.</hi> 2.13.</note> as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb facs="tcp:26950:11"/>ſpeaketh: and Hee is the God of Peace, and not of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33.</note> and ſuch is his lenitie in iudgement, as hee is loth to plucke his hand out of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, firſt offring compoſition, and a peaceable truce to the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and alwaies ſoundeth a friendly parlee of mercy, before his fearefull alarum of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and hence the Apoſtle truely calleth him, <hi>The God of patience and conſolation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.5. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>Hugo</hi> vpon theſe words, <hi>Trahe me,</hi> Draw mee, ſaith, That God draweth men vnto himſelfe, <hi>Aut terrendo minis, caedendo fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellis, aut blandiendo beneficijs, i</hi> Either by terrifying vs by me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ourging vs by iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or wooing vs by bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits; ſo that GOD neglecteth no oportunitie, and vſeth all
<pb facs="tcp:26950:12"/>meanes poſſible to reclaime ſinners, and to winſoules. And herewith he ſometimes vpbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>I ſrael:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 11.4.</note> 
               <hi>I led them with cords of a man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.7.</note> 
               <hi>euen with bonds of loue.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Zacharie</hi> in laying forth Gods delay in execution of his iudgements, ſecondeth him, whether the Prophet bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in God in the perſon, habit &amp; ſhape of a Shepheard, which leadeth his flocke with two ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall ſtaues, of ſundry names, and diuers properties: <hi>Nognam,</hi> and <hi>Chobelim, iucunditatem, &amp; diſsipantes,</hi> and as our tranſlation hath it, <hi>Bewty,</hi> and <hi>Bonds.</hi> So that Gods chiefe ſtaffe is Bewty, enamuled with rich iewels of mercie, and ſet with pretious pearles of bleſſings,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 17.8.</note> fairer then <hi>Aarons</hi> rodde flouriſhing with bloſſomes, and loaden with
<pb facs="tcp:26950:12"/>ripe almonds. And this ſheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooke God firſt holdeth vp in ſigne of mercy, and fauour, and pitie towards ſinners, and heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto alludeth the Kingly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet and Propheticall Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.1.</note> 
               <hi>Paſcens I ſraelauſculta, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens tanquam pecus Ioſeph.</hi> Thou which feedeſt <hi>Iſrael</hi> heare, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Ioſeph</hi> as a Sheepe. Now when this ſtaffe of Beauty beares no ſway, nor that we will not be ruled by this goulden Scepter of Beauty, then God breaketh it in his furie, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did the Tables of ſtone,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exed.</hi> 32.19.</note> and betaketh him to his other ſtaffe Bondes; and this is grieuous, <hi>It is a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing to fall into the hands of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.31.</note> And all this is nothing elſe but to manifeſt, how God delighteth in mercy, and how loth hee is at all times to execute
<pb facs="tcp:26950:13"/>iudgement. Thus God heere dealt with <hi>Sodom,</hi> who would not in any wiſe deſtroy it, if among manie thouſands hee coulde haue had but his tithe, ten righteous perſons, <hi>I will not deſtroy it for tens ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what ſhall I ſtand to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play the patience, longanimitie, and ſuffering forbearance of the Lord towards the firſt age, <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuy, Ieruſalem,</hi> or <hi>Sodom?</hi> Haue theſe places taſted, and ſeene the goodnes of the Lord aboue all others? Shall wee with the hartburning <hi>Iſraelites</hi> murmure and complaine:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exed.</hi> 17.7.</note> 
               <hi>Num Dominus in medio, an non?</hi> Haue not wee taſted, nay, haue not we ſurfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Lords mercie, and long ſuffering? O bleſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued and Chriſtian Citizens, euen this our <hi>Iſrael</hi> wherein we
<pb facs="tcp:26950:13"/>liue, this <hi>Canaan,</hi> which we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit, God in his patience and compaſſion hath had as vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant an eye ouer it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.12.</note> as euer he had ouer the holy land from the beginning of the yeare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end thereof, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of that fauourable aſpect, wherewith God hath alwaies, beheld, and vpheld this Land, and this people. I may ſay of it, as <hi>Syluius</hi> doth of <hi>Rhodes, Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in ſole ſita eſt Rhodos,</hi> The glorious ſunne-ſhine of Gods loue, the comfortable beames of his bleſſings, and the forcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e reflection of his mercies haue continually beene tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplendent through this region, and haue ouerſhadowed this land, as the Cherubins the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy-ſeate, as with this Iland,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exed.</hi> 25.28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hee hath not dealt ſo with euery nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26950:14"/>
            <p>Nay, euen this new <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the whole world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lament.</hi> 1.1.</note> great among Nations, and Princeſſe among Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, no place more then this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, hath in all treaſons, conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies, inſurrections, plagues, and other iudgements beene ſo much forborne, gently fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned and meaſurably puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that when the Lord God had as iuſt a quarrell againſt it, as euer hee had againſt <hi>Sodome,</hi> yet hee neuer deſtroied it, ſo that this people may ſing with the Prophet this encomiaſticke of Gods mercy, <hi>It is the Lond mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 3.22.</note> 
               <hi>that we are not conſumed, becauſe his compaſsions faile not.</hi> And all this while that I ſpeake of nothing elſe but the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God, this is a doctrine I know, That maketh vp the
<pb facs="tcp:26950:14"/>mouth of a worldling: O this ſweete loue-ſong of Gods long ſuffering, is a fit of muſicke fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a careleſſe carnaliſt, and to a diſſolute liuer it is like <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> ſtill pipe, which plaied <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> his hundred eies aſleepe at once. Yea, the whole world now adaies dreames on mercie, loueth to heare of mercie, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth of mercie, preſumeth on mercie, wholly groundeth on mercie, and hereby abuſe all Gods mercie, and becauſe God is ſo patient, and mercifull, they preſume thereof, and make too holde with God, tempting and prouoking him by continuall breach of his law, according to that of the Wiſeman, <hi>Becauſe ill workes are not preſentlie pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, men feareleſſe commit miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</hi> Thus <hi>Adam</hi> not ſeeing
<pb facs="tcp:26950:15"/>
               <hi>Euah</hi> preſently to die, ſtood a long time in a quandarie, <hi>&amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter precem mulieris &amp; praeceptum creatoris,</hi> as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaketh, betwixt his Wifes demaund, and his Creators commaund, at laſt thinking GODS word winde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 17.15.</note> reſolued, and did eate. Thus <hi>Iſrael</hi> gibed and ieſted at Gods threatnings by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: <hi>a ich debar Ichoua, iabo na,</hi> where is the word of the Lord? let it come now. Thus the Pſalmiſt inferreth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane abuſes of Gods mercie: <hi>Quomodo ſciuit Deus?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.11.</note> 
               <hi>Eſt ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia in excelſo? i.</hi> How came God to the knowledge of this? Is there knowledge in him aboue? And this contempt of Gods iudgements thundered out of his word, and this abuſe of Gods forbearance in not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying
<pb facs="tcp:26950:15"/>ſtroying, it was that crie which pearced the heauens from <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then to daſh the mirth of Mercy-men (which are the merry-men of the world) and to tell them what they are to hold vnto, for their preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mercy, abuſe of Gods pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and delay of repentance: who, though they liue neuer ſo diſſolutely, as though there were neither Heauen nor Hell, God, nor Diucll, yet if they may haue but one houre to repent, they aske no more, they are ſafe, and aſſure themſelues of ſaluation, if on their death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beds they haue but ſtrength and libertie to breath out a poore <hi>peccaui,</hi> and crie GOD mercie: <hi>Vox Diaboli non homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> The voice of a Diuell, not
<pb facs="tcp:26950:16"/>of a man. Of all ſpirituall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and giftes of God, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is the greateſt, which he daily offereth, and when hee ſeeth both his mercie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to bee skorned, and grow in contempt, that we ſtill liue in ſinne, neuer leaue ſinne, vntill wee bee readie to die in ſinne: what mercie can ſuch a wretch expect at his death, who hath abuſed Gods mercie all his life? And what kinde of repentance call ye that, when, if hee might haue liued anie longer, would neuer haue drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of repentance?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exed.</hi> 16.28.</note> It falleth out with Gods mercie, as with Manna, which God commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be gathered early in the morning, and reſerued too long became corrupt. So the true and heauenly Manna, the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
<pb facs="tcp:26950:16"/>of God, it is ſweeteſt, when it is gathered and apprehended in the golden morning of a mans youth, but when it is ſought in the euening,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 12.1.</note> in a mans dotage, and at a mans death, when a man is weakeſt, and not able to employ either hand, eye, eare, or tongue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135.17.</note> like an Idole. O this is a dangerous gathering of Manna, and an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable ſeeking of mercy, and to ſuch <hi>Auguſtine</hi> giueth a cold comfort: <hi>Maledictus, qui offert florem iuuentutis ſuae Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, &amp; faecem ſenectutis Deo reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat. i.</hi> Curſed is he, who offereth the prime of his youth to the Diuell, and reſerueth the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt dregs of his ould age for God. <hi>Gregory</hi> vpon the watches mentioned inthe Goſpell, ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.25.</note> that there bee three watches in
<pb facs="tcp:26950:17"/>a mans whole life, wherein it behoueth him to bee carefull, and as a wakefull and warie watch-man to keepe his watch. The firſt is Childhood, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Youth, and the laſt Olde age: So that he which remiſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſeth ouer his Childhood, let him be more carefull of his watch in Youth: and if he paſſe his Youth ouer his head diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, let him in any caſe looke to his laſt watch of Olde age. <hi>Nam quos diù, vt conuertantur, tolerat; non conuerſos duriùs dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. i.</hi> Thoſe whom God ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth long in hope of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, hee condemneth more grieuouſly not being conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: And therefore the holy Ghoſt giueth a ſhort day, <hi>Hodiè ſi vocem eius audierîtis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.7.</note> To day if ye will heare his voice.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26950:17"/>
            <p>This is the cauſe, why many and moſt rich men make bad and vncomfortable ends, and die ſo diſquietly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 2.29. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.33.</note> that with olde <hi>Simeon,</hi> they depart not in peace, and with <hi>Iacob,</hi> they plucke not their feete vp into the bed, for that, as <hi>Bion</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, a diſſolute life maketh a deſperate end. And ſurely for further veritie herein, I could yet neuer obſerue in my pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate experience, (which hath beene ſomewhat more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie in theſe caſes) that a worldly man, the man of earth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.20.</note> a morrow repenter, or a mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocker, who in his life hath chiefely followed the world, and the pleaſures and proffits thereof, euer made good end, or deſired to be diſſolued, but like <hi>Tantalus</hi> in hell (<hi>Auido fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaces
<pb facs="tcp:26950:18"/>captantem ore cibos</hi>) tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not to taſte of meate, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to fall in his mouth. Such at their endes, when they purpoſed to repent, had no minde, no ioy, nor power to repent, and when they preſumed of mercy, they periſhed in miſery: which the Wiſeman in his obſeruance complaineth of, and lamenteth: <hi>O Mors, quàm amara eſt tui memoria homini pacificè viuenti in his,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 41.1.</note> 
               <hi>quae ſunt cius?</hi> O Death, how bitter is thy ſting to a man that liueth ſecurely in his ſubſtance? So then for this point of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying or rather decaying re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and abuſe of mercy, I am of <hi>Bernards</hi> minde, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong infinite delaiers hardly one is ſaued and of <hi>Hieromes</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that ſuch liuers ſeldome or neuer make a good ende. Let
<pb facs="tcp:26950:18"/>then ſuch as liue deſperately without feare of iudgement, and yet die preſumptuous of mercy, bee packing with this <hi>mittimus,</hi> made by the prudent Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, <hi>Say not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>the mercy of the Lord is great, hee ſhall put away the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of my ſinnes: For mercy and wrath make haſte with him, and his indignation ſhall reſt vpon ſinners:</hi> and as it followeth in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth verſe, <hi>Put not off from day to day, for ſuddenly ſhall his wrath breake foorth, and when thou art without care and ſecure, thou ſhalt be deſtroied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let <hi>Sodomes</hi> deſtruction then become our inſtruction, and let it be a fearefull <hi>Foelix quem faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt,</hi> vnto all thoſe that feare not iudgements threatned, abuſe mercy offered, and deferre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance till the laſt caſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26950:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> the founder of your <hi>Milo,</hi> and tower of <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem</hi> (Chriſtian Citizens) gaue the Snaile in his Enſigne, with this Motto, <hi>Lentè festinandum,</hi> Softly and fafely: And Gods poeſy, although it be <hi>Tardus ad iram,</hi> Slow to wrath: and that with <hi>Qu. Fabius</hi> the Romane, <hi>Cunctando reſtituit rem,</hi> although God be long in comming, and flow in doing, and march faire and eaſie in puniſhing ſinne, yet at laſt, when God can forbeare no longer, nor endure our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities, nor brooke our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of his honourable mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 9.20.</note> then like <hi>Iehu</hi> the ſoone of <hi>Nimſhi,</hi> he marcheth furiouſlie, and at once hee payeth vs home for all:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Icre.</hi> 10.24.</note> and againſt this let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good man pray, <hi>O Lord cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect me, but with iudgement, not
<pb facs="tcp:26950:19"/>in thine anger, leaſt thou bring me to nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore, it reſteth yet, (and that appertinentlie) to conſider, why God eſpeciallie ſingled out <hi>Sodome,</hi> and chiefly bent his force againſt it, and wherein <hi>Sodome</hi> ſinned aboue all other places beſides, in ſo much that <hi>Sodome</hi> is famous, or rather infamous in the courſe of Scripture. Firſt, the people are ſaid to bee <hi>Cattaim ladonai meod, valdè, peccatores coram do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.13.</note> and againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.32.</note> 
               <hi>The Iewes vine is like the vine of Sodome and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah:</hi> and againe, <hi>They declare their ſinnes, as Sodome:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 39.</note> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>The iniquitie of my daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ieruſalem is greater then So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lamen.</hi> 3.6.</note> and againe, <hi>Contemners of the Goſpell ſhall haue eaſier iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then Sodome:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.15.</note> and againe,
<pb facs="tcp:26950:20"/>
               <hi>Sodom and the Cities there about were wicked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Jude</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>and made examples for vngodly liuers.</hi> Let vs then take a glaunce, if not a ſuruay of <hi>Sodoms</hi> ſinnes, and ſee what they were, for which God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroied them.</p>
            <p>The Spirit of God maketh no long beaderowle of them, but abſtracteth them, and like ſoure Coach-horſes which draw the Chariot of iniquitie, yoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them thus.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 16.49.</note> 
               <hi>Pride, Fulneſſe of bread, I dleneſſe, Contempt of the poore, this was the iniquitie of thy Siſter Sodom.</hi> What, were heere all <hi>Sodoms</hi> ſinnes, and all that God could obiect againſt it, or charge <hi>Sodome</hi> withall? Vnder this number of foure, their manifolde ſinnes are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, as <hi>For three tranſgreſſious of Damaſcus, and for foure, For
<pb facs="tcp:26950:20"/>three tranſgreſſions of Tyrus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>and for foure: For three tranſgreſſions of Moab, and for foure,</hi> whereby a multitude is meant. And as <hi>Leah</hi> called her firſt childe <hi>Gad Bagad,</hi> a companie commeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 30.11.</note> preſaging her increaſe of iſſue, ſo theſe foure mother ſinnes and capitall vices of <hi>Sodom</hi> had many fellowes, many followers and partners, like trait'rous <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalon</hi> and <hi>Achitophel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.12.</note> which by their flattery drew many mens hearts after them.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſinne of <hi>Sodome</hi> like to <hi>Pharaohs</hi> deſperate fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exed.</hi> 14.23.</note> which ſet firſt foote in the Sea, it is Pride, which alwaies loueth ſuperioritie and priori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. If there were ſeauenty times ſeauen deadly ſinnes, Pride would be firſt. Pride affecteth principalitie. Pride will haue
<pb facs="tcp:26950:21"/>the higheſt roome, and Pride is heere placed firſt, as <hi>Vriah</hi> by <hi>Dauid</hi> in the forefront of the battell.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.15.</note> And worthily hath Pride preheminence, for it was the firſt ſinne which vſurped heauen, intruded it ſelfe into Paradiſe, and hath now like conquering <hi>Alexander</hi> ouer-runne the whole world. <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia in caelo nata eſt, ſed velut im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memor, qua via cecidit, illàc nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam redire potuit,</hi> Pride, ſaith <hi>Hugo,</hi> was bread in heauen, but could neuer yet call to minde which way it fell, nor finde the way thither againe. And the Wiſeman ſaith more,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 10.3.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> i. Pride is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of ſinne. Since the fall of our great beldame <hi>Euah,</hi> Pride is held the womans ſinne. and poſted off to her, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb facs="tcp:26950:21"/>as to the weakeſt veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell. If therefore women would ſee themſelues and their pride in a glaſſe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7.</note> I referre them to the Prophets Criſtall, (it may bee called the womans Chapter) where God threatneth, and cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out againſt all the new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangled toies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 3.16.</note> infinite faſhions, and diſguiſed garments of that ſexe, whereby their Pride, as the Tauerne by the Yuy-buſh is deſcried for Sodomiticall. And for proud men otherwiſe in heart, which will be <hi>aut Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, aut nulli,</hi> commaunders, or no body; like to <hi>Saul,</hi> higher then any of the people by head and ſhoulders:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.2.</note> the Apoſtle ſtoppeth their mouths ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>God reſiſteth the proud.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>ames</hi> 4.6.</note> To this purpoſe it is memorable how the ancient Romains por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traitured
<pb facs="tcp:26950:22"/>Pride like the Diuell, with a triple Crowne on his head. On the firſt was ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Tranſcendo:</hi> on the ſecond <hi>Non obedio:</hi> on the third, <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbo.</hi> A proud man firſt aimeth at a high place of authority, then hee makes lawes and keepes none, but liueth as hee liſteth, and at laſt <hi>perturbat omnia Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uus,</hi> there is no quiet, no peace, where hee dwels, nothing but trouble and diſcontent. They that neuer ſaw a Pope, beholde this picture, and you ſhall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know whether hee bee a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domite or a Deuill. In a word, I will ſay no more of a proud man, then <hi>Innocentius</hi> will ſweare for mee, <hi>Omnis ferè vitioſus dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git ſibi ſimilem, ſolus ſuperbus odit ſuperbum:</hi> Whereas among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinnes the drunkard loues
<pb facs="tcp:26950:22"/>his fellow, the theefe his part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and the adulterer his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort: yet one proud man (if two bee neighbours) neuer brooketh the other, but like <hi>Eteocles</hi> and <hi>Polynices</hi> ſmoke, their breath is odious <hi>pro &amp; contrà.</hi> So that this proude ſinne, and ſinne of pride, it brought with it enuie, malice, hatred, wrath, diſcord, ſutes, quarrels, and breach of brotherly loue.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſinne of <hi>Sodome,</hi> is <hi>Fulneſſe of Bread,</hi> a ſin, whereof God gaue <hi>Iſrael</hi> warning afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, that when they ſhould come into the promiſed land of <hi>Canaan;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.11</note> and there had glutted themſelues, and were full, then beware, leſt thou forget thy Lord, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This was <hi>Baltazars</hi> ſinne who at his riotous banquet, in
<pb facs="tcp:26950:23"/>exceſſe of wine, amongſt his Princes, wiues and concubines; forgat the Lord ſo farre,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.6.</note> as Gods finger chalked his follie on the walles. In this fulneſſe ſinned churliſh <hi>Nabal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.11.</note> in forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of poore <hi>Dauid</hi> and his tired followers. And in this fulnes periſhed the giuttonous belly-god in the Goſpell, who would rather choake with the cruſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 16.21.</note> then hungerbitten <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> ſhould haue the crummes.</p>
            <p>O I feare me, Bleſſed Brethren that wee haue in theſe daies ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sodomites, boone compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and ſenſual good fellowes, quite drowned and ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in this ſinne of <hi>fulneſſe of bread and drinke.</hi> Theſe are thoſe beaſts,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32.</note> with whome the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle encountred at <hi>Epheſus</hi> after the manner of men, whoſe chiefe
<pb facs="tcp:26950:23"/>ſchoole point was this, <hi>Let vs eate and drinke, for to morrow wee ſhall die.</hi> Againſt theſe gorman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing Epicures God grieueth, and denounceth a woe, <hi>that eate the lambes of the flocke, and calues out of the ſtall, drinke wine in bowles, and annoint themſelues very coſtly, But no man ſaith he is ſorry for the affliction of Ioſeph.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 6.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And let mee the vnworthy meſſenger of God aggrauate my Lord and maiſters complaint and continue with homelie <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos</hi> a iuſt exclamation againſt luxurious drinkers, and inſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpunges, who ſee, that a great and ſmall cup can be but filled to the brimme: and yet they themſelues enforce their owne veſſels, and carcaſes to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerflow, and with the ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity of their fulneſſe drown them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:26950:24"/>not onely in drinke, but in a flood of wickednes. O what an horrible ſhame is it in <hi>Iſraell,</hi> when through ſimple ſnuffes of ſtrong drinke, and pure wine, many floures of chambers, and pauements in houſes are more moiſt &amp; ſlippery, then the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels in your ſtreets? Is not this alſo a ſin of <hi>Sodom,</hi> when the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting reuerſion of fatte tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers ſhall bee caſt vnder the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to dogges? Chriſt who for our ſakes often was an hungred neuer did it, vtterly miſliked it, and expreſſely forbad it, and <hi>Diues</hi> his dogges choſe rather to feede on <hi>Lazarus</hi> his ſoares,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.6. <hi>Luke:</hi> 16.21.</note> then of ſuch ſinfull diet. Right honorable, right worſhipfull, and Religious Citizens,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 26.2.</note> I will confeſſe with the Apoſtle, and thinke my ſelfe happy, that I
<pb facs="tcp:26950:24"/>ſpeake this day before them, who haue knowledge of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes and lawes, and therefore I beſeech you to heare me pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently. Among all politicall lawes of the Perſians, (which till this day are famous for their cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, there neuer was anie more profitable either to Gods Church, or the common wealth, then that of King <hi>Ahaſhueroſh,</hi> obſerued ſpecially in his owne Court for order of drinking,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſter.</hi> 1.8.</note> when none might compell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to drinke, but at euery mans pleaſure vnder paine of diſpleaſure. And not vnworthy is <hi>Plato</hi> reported for diuine, who forgat not this among his conſtitutions, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no man to drinke to another. But wee like ſwilling and ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Sodomites, drinke till
<pb facs="tcp:26950:25"/>our bellies breake in the midſt, as <hi>Iudas</hi> did:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 1.18.</note> drinke with <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth,</hi> that can draw vp Iordan into his mouth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 40.18.</note> taketh it with his eies, and thruſteth his noſe thorow, whatſoeuer meeteth him, and ten times worſe then beaſts that drinke for neceſſitie, we by onely drinking, metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phize our ſelues into beaſts. As excellently, as truly ſaid hee, <hi>Nos coelum terraemiſeemus,</hi> We mingle heauen and earth toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that is, the herbes and fruits of the earth, all variety of fiſh in the waters, all the fowles of the aire, all the ſtrong wines, odours, and ſpicerie procreate by the fire wee congeſt, and heape into a dunghill bellie, and all little ynough, and thus we ſinne with our Siſter <hi>Sodome</hi> in fulneſſe. Heere then (to ſhut
<pb facs="tcp:26950:25"/>vp this point) the diuine medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of abſtinent <hi>Auguſtine, Illud ante omnia rogo, &amp; per tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum diem iudicij vos adiuro, &amp;c.</hi> Brethren, ſaith he, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate you one thing aboue all the reſt, and thereunto I adiure you by the dreadfull day of iudgement, that as often as yee feaſt one another, ye would ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh one cuſtome out of your banquets, euen as the Diuels poiſon, namely, when as men meete, they vſe to drinke either voluntary, or vrged, <hi>grandi men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ura, ſine menſura, i.</hi> in great meaſure, without meaſure: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this vſe hath hitherto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained by tradition from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans and the Heathen, and therefore beſeemeth not a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of Ieſus Chriſt. And this ſinne of fulneſſe it ingendred
<pb facs="tcp:26950:26"/>riot, drunkenneſſe, whoredome, and forgetfulneſſe both of God and man.</p>
            <p>Next, followeth Idleneſſe, <hi>ſcelere ante alios immanior omnes,</hi> as bad as the worſt, and worſe then the reſt. That Idleneſſe is no ſmall ſinne, obſerue from the Creation, and ye ſhall find, that the Creator placed not <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> in <hi>Eden</hi> as an idle ſuruayer, to ſtand gazing, or to walke vp and downe till hee was weary but <hi>ad colendum, &amp; cuſtodien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> to till it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 2.15.</note> and keepe it. And ſo farre did God diſallow idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as hee by an edict and prohibition forbad idle beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging. In the Primitiue Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.2.</note> this was a great matter, which <hi>Paul</hi> ſound fault withall among his charge, <hi>Wee heare, that there
<pb facs="tcp:26950:26"/>are which walke among you inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>and worke not at all: Them, that are ſuch, wee commaund and exhort you by the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that they worke with quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and eate their owne bread:</hi> and to cut off ſuch rotten mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, he ſetteth downe a penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>Hee which will not worke let him not eate.</hi> Bleſſed beloued, I cannot iuſtly complaine of this <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> nor make your Citie Siſter to <hi>Sodome,</hi> (God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid) for idleneſſe, ſo might I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre <hi>Scandalum magnatum,</hi> and for my <hi>Vae vobis</hi> purchaſe a <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ram nobis,</hi> this place being an open enemy to idleneſſe, and farre from <hi>Sodome</hi> in this ſinne eſpecially. Why? heere are the aduenturous Merchants of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> which bring gould from <hi>Ophir,</hi> and Merchandize
<pb facs="tcp:26950:27"/>from <hi>Arabia.</hi> Heere is the curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hand of <hi>Hiram</hi> daily buſied in expert worke of braſſe. Here ye may heare melodious <hi>Iubal</hi> prayſing God earely and late on the muſicall inſtrument. Heere you may ſee the induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous labour of <hi>Tubal Cain</hi> in his yron worke. Heere is painefull <hi>Iabal,</hi> father of ſuch as dwell in Tents, and buy Cattell. Heere dwelleth laborious <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in Architecture. Heere liue <hi>Solomons</hi> prouident and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Ants, which in Summer make prouiſion for winter. And heere be <hi>Piſtrina ſocordiae,</hi> hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of correction for idleneſſe, and as ſtrict ſuruaying Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates for puniſhment of idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as euer was hard-hearted <hi>Pharaoh</hi> contrary to the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26950:27"/>
            <p>Notwithſtanding <hi>Longae ſunt Regum manus,</hi> that Magiſtrates haue long armes, and manie yeeres: yet <hi>latet anguis in herba,</hi> when <hi>Moſes</hi> was on the Mount,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.19.</note> 
               <hi>Iſrael</hi> plaid the wanton: and euen in this Citie (though not in the heart) yet in cloſe backe wings and obſcure angles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, there be many neſts full of idle birds, which the carefull Magiſtrate ſeldome findeth out. <hi>Ignauum fucos pecus à praeſepibus arcent,</hi> There is in the regiment of Bees an intruſiue and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Droane, which eateth vp the ſweete hony, for which the poore painefull creatures haue laboured for long before. And in the curious Bee-hiue of this commonwealth there are foure ſort of idle Bees, much like the foure Sects of Philoſophers,
<pb facs="tcp:26950:28"/>which ſometimes flouriſhed in <hi>Athens,</hi> the <hi>Academicke, Epicure, Peripatetique,</hi> and the <hi>Stoike.</hi> The firſt were greatly giuen to ſtudie and contemplation, and theſe are your idle gameſters, who are all night in ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, deuiſing new tricks, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting ſtrange conueyance by Cards and Dice, which next day they put in practiſe. God ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gent.</hi> 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>In the ſweate of thy face thou ſhalt eate thy bread,</hi> and theſe idle Bees liue by the ſweate of other mens browes, onely by playing.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.49.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> with one ſmooth ſtone out of his bag diſcomfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the whole hoaſt of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines: And this idle Gameſter with a blinde bone out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his iugling boxe, with the actiuity of a Polupragmaticall finger, can in one howre vndoe many
<pb facs="tcp:26950:28"/>a hopefull heire: I had almoſt ſaide, many an honeſt Trades<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Of the ſecond Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher the <hi>Epicure,</hi> I ſpake before in fulneſſe of bread, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I leaue him to his pleaſure, which is his <hi>Summum bonum.</hi> The third is the <hi>Peripateticke,</hi> who vſed to diſpute walking, and in this order are Cunny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catchers, who like the Diuell are alwaies compaſſing the Earth, and ſtill going vp and downe ſeeking whome they may dououre.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 2.2. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note> Theſe cunning Philoſophers walke from Inne to Inne, from Eaſt to Weſt, from Towrehill to Tyburne, (and there I leaue them) and with Sathan can turne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into an Angell of light, full of good words, and with <hi>Iudas</hi> embrace a man with a
<pb facs="tcp:26950:29"/>courtly boonecongee, and at parting cut a mans throate, and empoueriſh many a plaine dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling countrey gueſt with couſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage in copartnerſhip.</p>
            <p>The fourth idle Bee, or ſect of Philoſophers is the <hi>Stoike,</hi> who vſed to keepe their acts and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations ſtanding. And theſe I call your mimicall Comaedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and apiſh actors, who with <hi>Thraſo</hi> thunder out <hi>ſeſquipedalia verba,</hi> a heape of inkehorne tearmes to the tenour of a poore Colliar, and with a ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous <hi>Tu quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> moue many a foole to laugh at their owne follies. And further the licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Poet and Player together are growne to ſuch impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as with ſhameleſſe <hi>Shemei,</hi> they teach Nobilitie, Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, graue Matrons &amp; ciuill ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens,
<pb facs="tcp:26950:29"/>and like Countrey dogs ſnatch at euerie paſſengers heeles. Yea, Playes are growne now adaies into ſuch high re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt <hi>(Horreſco referens)</hi> as that ſome prophane perſons affirme, they can learne as much both for example and edifying at a Play, as at a Sermon. <hi>O tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, O mores,</hi> O times, O man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, tremble thou Earth, bluſh yee Heauens, and ſpeake O head, if euer any <hi>Sodomite</hi> vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered ſuch blaſphemie within thy gates. Did the diuell euer ſpeake thus impiouſly in this conflict with the Archangell?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude</hi> 9.</note> To compare a Iaſciuious Stage to this ſacred Pulpet and ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of trueth? To compare a ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken counterfeit to a Prophet, to Gods Angell, to his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to the diſtributer of Gods
<pb facs="tcp:26950:30"/>heauenly myſteries? And to compare the idle and ſcurrile inuention of an illiterate brick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layer, to the holy, pure, and powerſull word of God, which is the foode of our ſoules to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſaluation? Lord, forgiue them, they know not what they ſay.</p>
            <p>So that this Sodomitic all fin of idleneſſe is hatched vnder her wings another broode neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of Gods word, diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to authority, theft, and the very nurſerie of ſinne. Now I come to the laſt and leaſt ſinne of <hi>Sodome,</hi> Contempt of the poore, this commeth behinde all the reſt, aſhamed to ſhew it ſelfe, as the theeſe hanging backe from the barre. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of poore ſoules in this our yron age, their hard
<pb facs="tcp:26950:30"/>lodging at our barred gates, their continuall clamors in our ſtopped eares, and their ſlender reliefe from our ſhut hands, are able to make me to fill this San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary and holy place with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but Echoes of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: Charitie ſeemeth to bee ſo hard among vs, as thogh it were neuer heard of amongſt vs.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.6.</note> But as <hi>Moſes</hi> with one ſtroke of his rod enforced water from the flintie rocke, ſo my deſire is, that the hearts and ſoules of the vncharitable, mooued at this inſtant with my light touch of Charity, may hereafter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and powre foorth freſh ſprings and ſtreames of libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. Of all good works which wee doe in this life (and they are not many) there is none more acceptable to the Almighty
<pb facs="tcp:26950:31"/>then workes of mercy, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto Chriſt comfortably to encourage vs in our charitable courſe, promiſeth out of his free mercy an immortall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for reward.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.3.</note> 
               <hi>Come yee bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> And if rich men would aske me the high way to heauen, I would anſwere them as the ſonne of God did the young man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 19.21.</note> 
               <hi>Goe and ſell, and giue to the poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſpeaking of Contempt of the poore, this ſinne of <hi>Sodome,</hi> I beſeech you in a ſhort exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation onely (right Honourable, right Worſhipfull, and belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Lord) not to heare me, but the word of God, for I dare ſay with <hi>Iob, I am full of matter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 32.18.</note> 
               <hi>and the ſpirit within mee compelleth me. Demetrius</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> in the fiege of
<pb facs="tcp:26950:31"/>
               <hi>Rhodes,</hi> eſpecially tendred and preſerued the picture of <hi>Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes.</hi> And to rich men, ſuch as contemne the poore, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent for their fayring an image or picture to carrie with them into the Countrey, not to be hung in their Hals, or painted in their Parlors only,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 17.1.</note> but to be imprinted with a pen of yron, or the point of a diamond in the table of their hearts: and this picture it is the embleme or portraiture of Charity, to put them in remembrance of the poore,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.9.</note> and <hi>Let him that hath an eare to heare, heare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A naked Child, with a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Countenance, couered in a clowd, with a bloudie hart in the right hand, giuing hony to a Bee without wings. Now as <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſaid to his gueſts, <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:26950:32"/>yee had ploughed with my hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer yee could not haue found out my riddle:</hi> So this myſterie muſt haue an interpreter, and the meaning is this. Charity is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured a Child, becauſe the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable ought to bee humble, and curteous as a Child.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.2.</note> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riy is pictured naked, for that Charity ſeeketh not her owne.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</note> Charity looketh merily with a pleaſant countenance.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7.</note> God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a cheerefull giuer. Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is couered with a clowd: Almes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.2.</note> and workes of mercie ought to bee done priuately without vaine-glorie, or oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Charity holdeth a bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die heart in the right hand. A good man is mercifull and len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.5.</note> and his heart alwaies go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and agreeth with his hand. Charity offereth hony to a Bee
<pb facs="tcp:26950:32"/>without wings, that is, relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and helpeth ſuch poore, as for want of wings, for want of ſome limme, or member of their body, impotencie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie cannot labour for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, cannot worke for their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. And ſuch a practitioner in Charitie was that good and iuſt man <hi>Iob,</hi> as himſelfe (to the ſhame of our worldlings) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 29.12.</note> 
               <hi>I deliuered the poore that cried, and fatherleſſe, and him that had none to helpe him:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> I was eyes to the blinde, and feete to the lame.</hi> O I feare me, that wee haue many that beholde pictures, looke one <hi>Caeſars</hi> picture their coyne: but few that looke on, or like this picture of Charitie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 22.9.</note> or haue a good eie, that be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable to the poore.<note place="margin">Leuit. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> The Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiticall Prieſt entred once a
<pb facs="tcp:26950:33"/>yeare into the holieſt place: and the Romanes noted ſuch as once yearely entred not into their <hi>Templum Miſericordiae.</hi> Thus deale our rich Cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants in exerciſing Charitie, they once by the yeare perhaps reſpect the poore; nay, once in their liues; like the Swine, which is profitable at his death, or with the Mole, which ſeeth onely at her end, they at their deaths thinke they purchaſe heauen by a halfepenie dole, or a Chriſtmas dinner. O bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Brethren, and Chriſtian Countrimen, to wooe you from contempt of the poore, (for there is no compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt this charitable Citie, and the hard Countrey.) Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this one thing, <hi>Manas pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peris eſt gazophylacium Chriſti,
<pb facs="tcp:26950:33"/>&amp; quicquid pauper accipit, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus acceptat. i.</hi> The poore mans hand is Chriſts treaſurie, and looke, what the poore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth, Chriſt accepteth. Is the poore mans hand Chriſtes treaſurie? Is the poore mans boxe his Exchequer? O I feare me, Chriſt hath a poore ſtocke, an emptie Cheſt full of thankes in the one end, and ſtuffed with God helpe thee in the other, but not a pennie to ſupplie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 2.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, and beyond all this to ſtirre yee vp to Charitie, and to draw you from <hi>Sodoms</hi> ſinne, contempt of the poore: I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that the Apoſtle ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifieth three chriſtian vertues or ſiſters,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13.</note> which all at once came downe from heauen to get themſelues husbands on earth
<pb facs="tcp:26950:34"/>among the ſonnes of GOD Faith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 6.2.</note> Hope and Charitie. The elder ſiſter Faith, ſought her husband a great while, &amp; found none to her liking, vntill at laſt ſhee met and marched with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> by whom ſhee had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny children, and ſince that time hee is called the <hi>Father of the faithfull.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16.</note> Hope the younger ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter went ſomewhat longer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſped, many caſt an eie on Hope, and fed their fancies by Hope, but none could away to liue onely in Hope. At laſt comes <hi>Dauid,</hi> and hee without feare, diſtruſt, or delay, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth himſelfe, and marrieth with Hope: and ſhee proued ſo ſweete a ſpouſe, and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a wife vnto him, and ſo faithfull a helper in all his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, perſecutions and miſeries,
<pb facs="tcp:26950:34"/>as hee onely receiued comfort by her: yet my ſoule keepe thou ſilence vnto God, for my hope is in him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 62.5.65.5.146.5.</note> And againe, <hi>O thou the hope of all the ends of the earth:</hi> And againe, <hi>Bleſſed is hee, whoſe hope is in the Lord his God.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 142.5.</note> 
               <hi>I hope to ſee the Lord in the Land of the liuing.</hi> But for the yongeſt ſiſter Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, who was faireſt but poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, who had the beſt propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and worſt portion, ſhee wandreth ſtill vp and downe and findeth none that either minde her, or ſhee hath a minde vnto. This poore ſoule, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is yet on her pilgrimage, ſhee trauelleth from land to land, from nation to nation, from houſe to houſe, from doore to doore, and no man en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaineth Charitie, <hi>haec quia
<pb facs="tcp:26950:35"/>pauper erat.</hi> If Charitie come to the great and Noblemans gate, a grimme Porter preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly terrifieth her. If ſhee come to the Merchants doore, either a minſing maide, or a ſurly Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingman rebukes her. If ſhee chance to rap at the Porch of the Countrey Gentlemans manner-houſe, the Dawes from the Chimney toppe make her anſwere, <hi>Solitudo ante ostium,</hi> there is cold cheare, when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body keepeth houſe. If Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie knocke at the Clergies dore, O ſhee troubleth Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> at his Booke, with her Pater noſter, and ſo the prouerbe is verified, No pennie, No Pater noſter. If ſhee ſtumble on the Lawyers threſhold, he giueth her ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to couer her nakedneſſe, and ſendeth her away with a
<pb facs="tcp:26950:35"/>ſtatute lace for a largis. If ſhee trie farther the Phyſitions hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitality, he perhaps tendering her health leaſt ſhee ſhould ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit, purgeth Charitie with a bitter pill of contempt, or a ſpoonefull of diet drinke with <hi>God helpe.</hi> And thus in all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and conditions of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Charitie is contemned and excluded: Charity is reiected and abhorred; and no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile then, if Charity be cold, when neither winter nor ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, in court or countrie, citie or village, any man vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth Charity one nights lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging. O Lord, lay not this ſinne, Contempt of the poore to the charge of rich men. And this ſinne it brought couetouſneſſe, oppreſſion, vſury, iniuſtice, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, fraud and iniury, and
<pb facs="tcp:26950:36"/>where the poore is not releeued, God is little beleeued.</p>
            <p>What ſhall wee ſay then? Shall we accuſe <hi>Sodome,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe our ſelues? Were the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>Sodome</hi> greater ſinners then we? I muſt anſwere with the Meſſiah, <hi>I ſay nay, except yee repent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 13.3.</note> 
               <hi>ye ſhall all periſh.</hi> For let vs weigh their ſinnes and ours in an equall ballance, and iumpe both of them together vpon the weights, and trie which is heauieſt; and caſt them vp all in a groſſe ſumme, and ſee, which are moſt in number. What ſhall I ſpeake of oathes, blaſphemies, and ſwearing in Faires, and Shops in bargaining; yea, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Children in the ſtreetes who can ſooner and more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſweare by the name of God, then they can tell their
<pb facs="tcp:26950:36"/>owne names. Are not wee as bad as <hi>Sodome?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſpeake of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning the Lords Saboath, by idle walking in fields, and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in obſcure corners, whilſt the food of our ſoules is in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributing? Is not this a ſinne of <hi>Sodome?</hi> For luſt and ſecret whoredome,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 30.20.</note> like <hi>Salomons</hi> har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot wiping our lips, as though all were well:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 38.18.</note> Wee with <hi>Iudah</hi> difcry our ſelues and filthineſſe by our ſignet, cloake, and ſtaffe: nay, the horrible and nameleſſe ſinne of <hi>Sodome</hi> hath poiſoned ſome. And are we inferiour to <hi>Sodom?</hi> For falſhood, deceit, flattery, diſſimulation, crueltie, and vſurie, wee can boldly ſay with <hi>Iob. Our iniquitie is ſealed vp in bagges:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.17.</note> 
               <hi>and this age goeth farre beyond Sodome.</hi> Name me anie
<pb facs="tcp:26950:37"/>ſinne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.19.</note> yea Idolatry, and you ſhall finde many <hi>Labans</hi> with his woodden gods, cloſe Papiſts at their beades, and many illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Leuites playing the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Maſſe Prieſts in <hi>Micah</hi> his houſe for ten ſickels of ſiluer by the yeare,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 17.10.</note> a ſuite of apparell, meate and drinke: ſuch are iugling Ieſuites, and ſecret Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries, inueigling ſimple ſoules for their penny-father Pope: O this is at leaſt a ſinne of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and a damnable ſinne of the whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.4.</note> the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> So that if <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſaid of his ſinnes, <hi>That they were gone ouer his head, and a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then too heauie for him to beare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">40.12.</note> 
               <hi>and moe in number then the haires of his head:</hi> O what ſhall we ſay of our ſinnes? euen with <hi>Iob.</hi> 9.20. <hi>If I ſhould iustifie my ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:26950:37"/>mine owne mouth ſhall condemne mee.</hi> And if God for foure ſinnes thus handled <hi>Sodome</hi> by fire, O how ſhall hee deale with Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Country Townes <hi>(ſic magnis componere parua ſolebam)</hi> wherein many moe ſinnes, and more grieuous ſinnes daily raigne, then euer did in <hi>Sodome.</hi> And ſurely, that God is thus forbearing, wee muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his loue and long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and ſay with thankefull <hi>Iacob, Wee are not worthie of the leaſt of all thy mercies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 32.10.</note> And now I come at laſt, though long, to the ſecond part and partie of my diuiſion, namely in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> the ſympathie and feeling compaſſion of the faithfull for their afflicted and ſinfull bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
            <p>It is ſaide of <hi>Hippocrates</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:26950:38"/>twinnes, that they alwaies loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked each on the other, and in action imitated one another, which affection ought to be in all Chriſtians one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.13.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to laugh with them that laugh, and weepe with them that weepe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely, this affection and tender heart hath alwaies beene in Gods ſeruants (as wee may obſerue) for Gods people, their ſinnes, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. Thus zealous <hi>Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> when hee ſaw the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple dauncing about the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den calfe, brake forth for griefe in ſorrow of his ſoule for their ſinne:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.31.</note> 
               <hi>Either ſpare them O Lord, or race mee out of the booke which thou haſt written.</hi> Thus <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> mourned for <hi>Sauls</hi> reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15 35.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:26950:38"/>Thus the Prophet fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing in the ſpirit Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hanging ouer the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for ſinne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 24.16.</note> cried out <hi>Razi li, razi li, O li: bogedim bagedu, vbeged, bogedim, bagedu,</hi> that is, <hi>My ſecret, my ſecret, woe is me: The tranſgreſſours haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, the tranſgreſſours haue grieuouſly offended.</hi> Thus was <hi>Ieremie</hi> grieued in his ſpirit for Iſrael:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 8.21.</note> 
               <hi>I am ſore vexed for the hurt of the daughter of my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 9.1.</note> 
               <hi>O that mine head were full of waters, and mine eies a fountaine of teares, to weepe day and night for the ſlaine.</hi> This compaſſion was in his brother Prophet,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 9.8.</note> 
               <hi>Ah Lord God, wilt thou deſtroy all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of Iſrael, in powring out thy wrath vpon Ieruſalem?</hi> And as pitifullie complaineth <hi>Daniel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.16.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:26950:39"/>
               <hi>O Lord, according to all thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, I beſeech thee, let thine anger, and thy wrath be turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Am.</hi> 7.2.</note> Neither was the <hi>Thecoite</hi> Heards-man behind them in commiſeration, <hi>Spare I beſeech thee, for who ſhall raiſe vp Iacob, for hee is ſmall?</hi> and ſo the Lord repented for this.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ion.</hi> 4.5.</note> Thus alſo <hi>Ionah</hi> ſolitarie in his cell and booth without the Citie-gate mourned for <hi>Niniuie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marke</hi> 3.5.</note> Yea, this liuely feeling of our brethrens infirmities was in Chriſt hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who ſorrowed for the hard heart of the Synagogue, and prophecying the deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41.</note> he wept ouer it. And in his Maiſters ſteps wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed himſelfe to be ſeperated from Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.3.</note> for his brethren his kinſemen according to the
<pb facs="tcp:26950:39"/>fleſh. And laſtly in this place, righteous <hi>Lot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8.</note> who ſate at the gate of <hi>Sodom,</hi> was inwardly vexed for the Citizens ſinnes, and puniſhments menaced by God for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Take this then (bleſſed Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) for a manifeſt ſigne of the childe of God, and a true marke of a good man, to be ſory for his brethren, and to grieue at their puniſhment for ſinne. But where ſhall wee ſingle out amongſt the ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> a compaſſionate <hi>Abraham?</hi> an humble ſuiter for <hi>Sodome?</hi> or a man ſorrowing for ſinne in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother? <hi>Hagar</hi> indeed mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for <hi>Iſmael, Iacob</hi> for <hi>Ioſeph: Ioſeph</hi> for <hi>Beniamin,</hi> the Iſraeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh virgins for <hi>Iephthaes</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Marie</hi> for <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and we for the deceaſſe and departure
<pb facs="tcp:26950:40"/>of our friends, <hi>&amp; hinc illae la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymae.</hi> But if wee ſee our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, neighbour, or familiar, to be a vitious liuer, wedded to wickedneſſe, and ſunke in ſinne, we ſalue it vp with <hi>Humanum eſt,</hi> ſo that now adaies ſinne in young men is nothing but a tricke of youth, and in ould men an infirmitie of age, and heere is all the reckoning wee make of ſinne. <hi>Cato</hi> the graue Senator of <hi>Rome</hi> was obſerued neuer to laugh, but once, and that was, when he eſpied out of his caſement an Aſſe eating thiſtles, that the ſenceleſſe beaſt ſhould take pleaſure in pricks, which ſhould haue been ſpurres vnto him to take paines. So we, ſeeing our brethren eating vp ſinne as bread, and drinking ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie as water, rather laugh
<pb facs="tcp:26950:40"/>with <hi>Democritus</hi> at their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, then with <hi>Heraclytus</hi> lament their faults. Shall I ſpeake plainely? Thoſe, that make a Maygame of ſinne in others, laughing at a drunkard in the channell, applauding a ſwag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerer in his blaſphemies, and as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.28.</note> running with a theefe, and taking part with the adulterer: they are brethren to curſed <hi>Cham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.22.</note> who ſeeing his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged father in a drunken fitte, blabbed it to his brethren in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion and contempt, when rather he ſhould haue concealed it and ſorrowed for it.</p>
            <p>The Elephant, as naturall Hiſtorie teſtifieth, if he meete a wounded perſon wandring in the wilderneſſe, ſafely condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth him therein: and the like is fathered on the Dolphine,
<pb facs="tcp:26950:41"/>who, when <hi>Arion</hi> was caſt into the Sea, ſpeedily conueyed him to the ſhore. I could wiſh, that after the preſident of our father <hi>Abraham</hi> in this place towards ſinfull <hi>Sodome,</hi> we were either Elephants or Dolphins in ſparke of good nature one to another, when rather wee ſeeme Lions and Dogs: to pity one another, to ſorrow for anothers ſinne, and to pray one for another. The neighbourly <hi>Samaritane,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 10.34.</note> to the poore paſſenger may teach vs this leſſon: his wounds reſemble afflicted finners: his deſcenſion from <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richo,</hi> his fallng from the Church of God, his ſpoiling by theeues, ſinners ouerthrow by Sathan: The Prieſt and Leuite, which went aloofe, <hi>Sunt mali Eccleſiae miniſtri,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lyra, Curantes tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum
<pb facs="tcp:26950:41"/>de leuatione pecuniae, non ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione culpae.</hi> Like our Romiſh Prieſts, which eaſe a man of his money, but neuer heale his ſin, or helpe his ſoule. Now the good <hi>ſtraunger, Infundens oleum miſericordiae &amp; vinum iuſtitiae:</hi> It is any good man mooued in pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and piety at a ſinners wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched eſtate, who powreth in the oile of commiſeration, and wine of rightcouſnes, and vſeth all meanes poſſible to reclaime him, and cure his infirmities.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe tendeth the counſell of the Apoſtle: <hi>Beare yea one anothers burden.</hi> And as Chriſt ſtretched forth his hand,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2.</note> and caught faſt hold on <hi>Peter,</hi> when hee was ready through weaknes to ſinkeon the ſea: So ought wee towards our ſinfull brethren, ouerwhelmed with
<pb facs="tcp:26950:42"/>the waues of wickedneſſe, to haue compaſſion on them, to lament their deſperate conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and by our good aduiſe and counſell, and comfort out of the word of God to ſaue their ſoules: and this is to ſhew our ſelues with <hi>Abraham</hi> heere, to be the children of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> greatly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth this worke, and thus perſwadeth vnto it: <hi>Piaeſt illa triſtitia alienis vitijs ingemiſcere, non adhaerere: contriſtari, non implicari: dolore contrahi, non attraht.</hi> This is godly ſorrow indeede to pittie mens ſinnes, not to be polluted by them: to ſorow for them, not to ſinke in them: to be withdrawne in dolour, not drawne vnto them by delight. And when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, how backward we are in
<pb facs="tcp:26950:42"/>this point of Chriſtianitie, to haue a patheticall feeling and liuely touch of a ſinfull mans miſerie, and an inward griefe for iudgements due for their ſinnes: Then I remember Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> his complaint in his time for ſuch defect of dnetie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men: <hi>Cadit aſinus, &amp; eſt qui ſubleuet: per it anima, &amp; non eſt, qui curet,</hi> Firſt the Aſſe fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth into the ditch, and hee fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a helper by and by: but the ſinfull ſoule periſheth, and no man taketh care. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are like the baſe minded <hi>Gergeſenes,</hi> who had more care ouer their ſwine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.25.</note> then their ſoules. O bleſſed brethren and Chriſtian Citizens, this one ſin want of compaſſion and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly affection hath poſſeſſed head and taile, better and worſe,
<pb facs="tcp:26950:43"/>and all conditions and callings.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 9.15.</note> O where ſhall wee find a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſinne, a reprehender of ſinne, a mourner for iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, executed for ſinne, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimer of ſinners, or with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> a pitifull petitioner to God for ſinfull <hi>Sodome?</hi> The indulgent parent ioyeth in his lewde children, and applaudeth his prodigall <hi>Abſalon,</hi> as olde <hi>Eli</hi> did his ſonnes, and thinketh all well without any contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or correction of their ſins, The pampering mother glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in her proude darling, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in her pride, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth her in all laſciuiouſnes, as <hi>Herodias</hi> did her dauncing tripped <hi>Salomon,</hi> and findeth no fault in ſinning. Looke further among all ſortes of men, and ſee how remiſſe euery man is in
<pb facs="tcp:26950:43"/>this point, to reclaime his neighbour, to reprehend his brother, or to rebuke a ſinfull perſon. Yea, this ſinne of flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering men in ſinne is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies gone ſo far, and hath infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſo many: as it is ſometimes found in the houſe of <hi>Leui,</hi> and in the Schooles of the Prophets, and againſt this God crieth out in high diſcontent:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>From the Prophet to the Prieſt euery man dealeth falſely, for they haue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the hurt of the daughter of my people with ſweet words, ſaying Shalom, Shalom, Veen Shalom,</hi> Peace, peace, and there is no peace. And ſurely (bleſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) as it is odious in the ſight of God: ſo it is hatefull to euery good man, when a mealy mouth Miniſter ſhall ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficially and nicely glaunce
<pb facs="tcp:26950:44"/>ouer ſinne, as men walke onice. When Miniſters (who ought to bee <hi>Boanerges</hi> the ſonnes of thunder, as Chriſt called <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi>)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marke</hi> 3.17.</note> when they, I ſay, ſhall either feare with ſmoothing <hi>Zidkijah</hi> to ſpeake the truth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 22.24.</note> or forbeare with white-liuered <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maziah</hi> to rip vp the bowell of ſinne:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Am.</hi> 7.13.</note> I make no better of ſuch temporizers, then of forſworne and vnconſcionable Country Church-wardens, who prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Omnia benè,</hi> when all the pariſh is out of ſquare. <hi>Iob</hi> vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly miſliked this,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 32.22.</note> 
               <hi>I may not giue titles to man, leaſt my maker take me away ſuddenly.</hi> And the Apoſtle was afraid thereof, <hi>If I ſhould pleaſe men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galy.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>I were not the ſeruant of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs all then (Bleſſed bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) imitate the life of our
<pb facs="tcp:26950:44"/>faithfull father <hi>Abraham:</hi> let vs with him ſorrow and grieue for our ſinfull brethren: let vs with <hi>Abraham</hi> pray for <hi>Sodom:</hi> and let vs after the example of <hi>Abraham</hi> entreat God, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour him by continuall praiers to be mercifull to ſinners. And herein we ſhall performe that excellent worke commended by the ſonne of wiſedome <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 11.30.</note> Lekak Nepaſhoth Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kam, i. <hi>He is wiſe, that winneth Soules.</hi> To fold vp this part in a narrow plaite, and to winde vp in a word: there is no ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt ſigne of true loue, and godly friendſhip among men, as one to finde fault with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ſinne, and to rebuke a friend for his inordinate life. And therefore howſoeuer <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio</hi> diſtaſted <hi>Bias</hi> in opinion,
<pb facs="tcp:26950:45"/>
               <hi>Ama, tanquam oſurus:</hi> I take his meaning thus, that wee ought ſo to loue a friend, as therewithall we ſhould hate his bad conditions, &amp; embrace the man, but hate his manners: and this is the priuate duty of one towards another, and a Chriſtian office, which ought to bee found in the heritage of <hi>Iacob.</hi> And among many mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall praecepts and ciuill Lawes eſtabliſhed by God himſelfe in the common wealth of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> this was enacted for one:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19.17.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thine heart,</hi> but <hi>thou ſhalt plainely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke thy neighbour, and ſuffer not ſinne vpon him.</hi> And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle hath a worthy ſaying. <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge your faults one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>and pray one for another, that ye may be healed: For the praier of
<pb facs="tcp:26950:45"/>the righteous auaileth much, if it be feruent. Salomon</hi> ſhutteth it vp thus:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 27.5.</note> 
               <hi>Open rebuke is better then ſecret loue. But more plaine is the holy Ghoſt by the Prophet: Shubu, Vehaſhebu,</hi> Returne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eze.</hi> 13.30.</note> and cauſe others to returne: and that man, which retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth himſelfe to the Lord, and with him maketh others to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne: hee mav ſit downe and ſay with ould <hi>Iacob</hi> ioyfull of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> life. <hi>Rab,</hi> I haue ynough.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thus at laſt I come to the laſt part, namely, in <hi>Sodome,</hi> wherein ten righteous perſons could not bee found) the ſmall number of the elect, and few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of good and faithfull men in the Church. The eſtate and condition of the Church of God is elegantly ſet foorth by the princely Preacher of <hi>Iſrael
<pb facs="tcp:26950:46"/>Solomon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 9.14.</note> 
               <hi>A little Citie and few men in it &amp;c.</hi> This ſmall City with few men in it repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Church militant on earth, which is daily aſſaulted by the ſtrong man vp in armes Sathan,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 11.21.</note> and was deliuered by the pollicy of the poore wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.3.</note> and yet none is thank full for his paines, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one to tenne, as it fell out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the leapers. So that whereas <hi>Babylon</hi> is ſaid to bee a great City,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 17.17.</note> and <hi>Niniuy</hi> to bee very ſpatious;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.28.</note> forty and odde miles about:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.2.</note> yet the Church of God is but a little one, and as it is ſmall, ſo there be but a few therein. This was apparent in all ages, that moſt in the world were badde, and that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Sathan alwaies excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Gods. At the deluge the
<pb facs="tcp:26950:46"/>wickedneſſe of man was great, and the whole world corrupt, and there were onely eight, that found grace in the ſight of the Lord. Iuſt <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in <hi>Aegypt, tanquam Roſa inter ſpinas,</hi> as a rate roſe among a world of thornes. <hi>Iob</hi> in the land of <hi>Huz,</hi> a blacke Swanne, to keepe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vpright in an heathen Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Nicodemus</hi> the night-wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> and a ſmall handfull of others in the whole Synagogue of the <hi>Iewes.</hi> And in this City of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> (beſides <hi>Lot</hi> and his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould) God appoſed citie and ſuburbs with the number of tenne. The Arke of <hi>Noah</hi> prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured this paucity and defect of the faithfull, and of ſuch as ſhould bee ſaued in the Church, when the number of vncleane
<pb facs="tcp:26950:47"/>beaſts exceeded the number of the cleane. And euen in theſe daies, when the whole world ſwarmeth with multitudes of people, and men ſurpaſſe in number the moates in the ſunne, and ſands on the ſhore. If GOD ſhould looke from heauen,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 14.3.</note> or come in progreſſe to iudgement, hee ſhall finde but a few good, hardly fifty in a Citty, tenne in a Corporation three in a village, two in a houſe good: nay, I feare mee greatly we would ſend him away diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, as from <hi>Sodome,</hi> for want of ten righteous perſons, and cut him ſhort of his tith. It is no meruaile then, if God call his Church a Vineyard,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 5. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 80.8.</note> which is but a ſmall ſpot, and a little plot in reſpect of the ſlender quantity of vines, which it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth
<pb facs="tcp:26950:47"/>and euill quality of grapes, which it affordeth.</p>
            <p>The ancient <hi>Hebrewes</hi> giue an ingenious and exquiſite reaſon, why the great name of God <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is written almoſt in all nations and tongues, onely with foure letters. The Iewes call him <hi>Iehouah,</hi> the Grecians <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Latiniſts <hi>Deus,</hi> the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians <hi>Thewt,</hi> the Perſians <hi>Syros,</hi> the Arabians <hi>Alla,</hi> the French <hi>Dieu,</hi> the Germans <hi>Gott:</hi> to import, that in the foure parts of the world both to the Iew and Gentile, his name is known, and that God hath his Church euery where: and if not tenne, as in <hi>Sodome,</hi> yet can hee find ſome, which bee his, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they bee of no note or account in the world:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.5.</note> 
               <hi>There is a remnant through the election of
<pb facs="tcp:26950:48"/>Grace.</hi> This was that comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table anſwere, which God gaue to iealous <hi>Elijah,</hi> when hee was out of all heart for the ſmall number of Gods Children. I can find ſeuen thouſand in Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 9.18.</note> that neuer bent knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> or kiſſed him with their mouth; So likewiſe the ſeede,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.8.</note> that was ſowne in foure ſeuerall grounds, the fourth part of it tooke root and fructified:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</note> and whereſoeuer <hi>Paul</hi> planteth, or <hi>Apollo</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth, all labour is not loſt, in ſome God will giue increaſe, and among an heape of hearers God hath a ſecret number, which are his. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that not onely a ſmall number are elect: but hee ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth alſo, of what manner they be, which are of Gods Church. <hi>Not many wiſe and mighty after
<pb facs="tcp:26950:48"/>the fleſh are called, but poore and vile, and things which are not. And</hi> Herome conſidering this, ſaid: <hi>Eplchecula pauper cula Eccleſin, The Church conſiſteth of the ſimpleſt ſort and me aueſt men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then as in the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of <hi>Sodome, Lot</hi> ſecured himſelfe in the little Citie, <hi>Bela</hi> or <hi>Zoar</hi> for his ſanctuary,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.20.</note> and ſo eſcaped Gods vengeance and puniſhment: So (right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, right Worſhipfull and bleſſed Brethren).<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.1.</note> I beſeech and exhort you by the comming of our Lord Ieſus, and by our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling vnto him, that your conuerſation bee holie, and in godlineſſe: that whenſoeuer the Lord ſhall threaten ſtorme and tempeſt vpon ſinners, of fire and brimſtome, as on <hi>Sodom:</hi> we may bee aſſured of little <hi>Zoor</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:26950:49"/>for our refuge and receptacle, that Gods Church may bee our defence: that we be ſure, we be not onely of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.6.</note> but <hi>Iſrael,</hi> members of the Church, and in the ſmall number of Gods elect. This was the daily praier and meditation of <hi>Nazianze.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>Quaere ratem <hi>Noae,</hi> vt mortis</l>
               <l>diſcrimina vitem.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So that without this <hi>Arke</hi> of Gods Church there is no ſafety in this life, nor ſaluation in the next.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Non Deus huic Pater eſt, cui non</l>
               <l>Eccleſia mater.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Among all the heauenly and powerfull wordes which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the <hi>Mcſsiah,</hi> there is none in my minde more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, or ſtirring to make a man
<pb facs="tcp:26950:49"/>mindfull of himſelfe, then this; <hi>Many are called, but few are choſen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.16.</note> And verily a right bad man, if he well and rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this point, the ſmall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the elect, and thoſe that ſhall be ſaued: it will make him cry out with <hi>Balaam; Let my ſoule die the death of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 23.10.</note> 
               <hi>and let my laſt end bee like his. Praeclara rara,</hi> choiſe things are moſt rare, as we may obſerue in nature. Of ordinary ſtones there are ſtore, but pretious ſtones are ſcan: vnprofitable herbes grow euery where, but g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aine and flowers more ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly: and in the Church there bee many, but few which are Gods, many veſſels, but few of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor: &amp; therefore our Sauiour en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth his handfull and ſmall company:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32.</note> 
               <hi>Feare not little flocke</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:26950:50"/>There is one ſpeech vtterd by the Apoſtle, which as often as I thinke on, ſo oft doe I feare, and tremble:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.28.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord will make a ſhort count on the Earth.</hi> Where there is a ſmall flocke, a ſhort count will ſerue the turne. A Bill of few parcels is ſoone ſummed: And the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete number both of the elect and caſtawaies being knowne before hand to the Lord: the audit at the day of iudgement will bee very ſhort, and hee will make a quicke diſpatch at the generall Aſſiſe of the glorious Reſurrection when he ſhall giue ſentence of life and death.</p>
            <p>Fathers, Men, and Brethren, and all yee, (that heare mee this day) there is none here preſent, but he aſſureth himſelfe, that his name is regiſtred in the
<pb facs="tcp:26950:50"/>Booke of life: eueric man ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth to be ſaued: Saluation is the golden Bell, for which we all runne: Saluation is the marke, whereat wee all aime: and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie man hath one foot (as hee thinkes) alreadie in Heauen. To encourage all, and to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimate none in their courſe, a man may eaſily reſolue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, whether he be in the right way, or no: in the high way towards Heauen, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently know alſo, if hee bee in the number of the elect, by that direction and rule taught by our Saufour:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mate.</hi> 7.13.</note> 
               <hi>Enter in at the ſtraight gate, for it is the wide gate and broadway, that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there bee, which goe in thereat: Becauſe the gate is ſtraight, and the way nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, that leadeth vnto life, and
<pb facs="tcp:26950:51"/>few there he that finde it.</hi> Heere are propoſed two waies, and two gates, which all the world walke in and enter in at, the wide gate and broad way, the narrow way, and ſtraight gate. The firſt is the broad cart-way, and wide ſtaring gate, which leadeth to Hell, and a blind man may hit it, and many goe thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The other is a little foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>path ſcarce beaten, and a ſtraight portall to Heauen, and a farre traueller often miſſeth it, and this is found of very few. Note as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to his, ſo I to you,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>Proue and examine your ſelues,</hi> which of theſe two waies ye walke in, and which of theſe two dores ye looke within: and then ſhall it be ſeene, whether yee bee in the number of moſt and worſt, or in the number of
<pb facs="tcp:26950:51"/>feweſt and beſt, and whether yee ſhall be ſaued or damned.</p>
            <p>Doeſt thou walke in the old way, which is the good way?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 6.16.</note> Art thou ſtrict and preciſe in faſting and praying?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.14.</note> Art thou ſtraight girt about with verity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.13.</note> and the goulden girdle of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencie?<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>119.</hi>
               </note> Doeſt thou narrowlie keepe thy feete from euery euill way, that thou maieſt obſerue the word? Doeſt thou not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a multitude to doe euill,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.2.</note> nor the world by the broad way, and wide gate?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſu.</hi> 20.13.</note> Doeſt thou ſet downe thy reſt with <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> I and my houſe will ſerue the Lord? O this is a ſigne, that thou art the childe of God, and booked among the number of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and that thou art ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aled for the ſeruant of God in thy forehead among the Tribes of
<pb facs="tcp:26950:52"/>the children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The more I conſider this point, that the whole City of <hi>Sodome</hi> could not affoord tenne righteous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and how ſmall a number there is in Gods Church prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinated to ſaluation: when I thinke, that the huge Monarchy of Sathan farre exceedes the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Ariſtocratie of God: how at the laſt day Hell ſhall be thrun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and crowded full of repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates, and heauen empty in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, and few faued: So long am I bound hand and foote from ſinning, and ſinne all this while hath no power to raigne in my morniall body, and this was the heauenly vow and diuine medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of <hi>Anſelmus: Si hinepecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; illina infernum habereus, ac vni corum neceſſriò immergi deberem: priùs me in infernum
<pb facs="tcp:26950:52"/>demergerem, antequam peccatum committerem.</hi> If (ſaith he) Hell were on one ſide, and Sinne on the other, and that perforce I muſt into one of them: I would firſt, runne headlong into Hel, before that I would meddle with ſinne. O ſanctified ſoule! O mortified breaſt! how farre doe wee digreſſe from this reuerent aduertiſment, of this bleſſed Saint?</p>
            <p>To temper all my ſpeech by the time, I will make my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion an exhorration, drawne out of Chriſts Sermon concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his ſecond comming to iudgement:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 17.34.</note> wherein hee war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs to be watchfull and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and not ſecure or diſſolute, as in the daies of <hi>Noah.</hi> For (ſaith he) two ſhall bee in one bed, the one receiued, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:26950:53"/>left: two in the field, one receiued, and his fellow forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: And ſeeing at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Sonne of man in his glorie there ſhall bee a ſeperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.32.</note> either on the right hand for ſheepe, or on the left hand for goates: Let vs all I beſeech you, ſtriue and endeauour to be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among thoſe that ſhall bee receiued: and that wee may be counted ſheepe of the Lords hand and people of his paſture, like <hi>Iacobs</hi> coloured ſheepe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 20 41. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.7.</note> let vs get vs forth by the tents of the ſhepheards.</p>
            <p>Firſt, therefore as yee haue heard (Bleſſed Beloued) of the longanimity, long-ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and patience of the Lord in executing iudgement, and puniſhing ſinne in his forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of <hi>Sodome,</hi> with which hee
<pb facs="tcp:26950:53"/>would in no wiſe haue dealt rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly: Let vs all bee warned heereby, how wee abuſe Gods goodneſſe and clemency, by praeſumption of mercy, delay of repentance, and contempt of his menaces: <hi>Let vs not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the riches of his bountifulneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>but know that the bountifulneſſe of God leadeth thee to repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in <hi>Abraham,</hi> who became an humble ſuter to God for <hi>Sodome:</hi> Let vs as the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Abraham,</hi> when wee ſee our brethren ſunke in ſinne, looſe in life, and that they haue ſold themſelues to worke wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe (as it was ſaid of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab:</hi>) Let vs ſorrow for them,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King</hi> 21.</note> pray to God for them, and vſe all meanes to conuert them: and let vs with the mercifull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make merry at the returne
<pb facs="tcp:26950:54"/>of our prodigall brother,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 16.10.</note> and with the bleſſed Angels re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce at the conuerſion of a ſinner.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, in that the whole Citie of <hi>Sodome,</hi> was ſtalled with tenne good men, and could not yeeld them to God, let populous Cities and great places make ſure, that there may alwaies bee found among them a righteous <hi>Lot,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the number of tenne, yea rather tenne thouſand recorded in the writing of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And let priuate families, and euerie houſhold take heede, that when the Lord ſhall come at his generall viſitation through our ſtreetes, and paſſe along by our houſes, that then the poſtes of our dores bee ſound
<pb facs="tcp:26950:54"/>ſprinkled with the blood of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ambe, that ſo God may ſtalke vs, and that the plague of deſtruction may paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer our heads. Yea, let vs all with faithfull <hi>Rahab</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play out of our windowes a redde carnation ribbin died in the blood of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> that God may thereby know vs, and haue mercy on vs at his comming to diſſolue the World. That then wee may bee taken vp from the tents of <hi>Keder,</hi> and out of this vale of miſerie, to bee infranchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Cittizens in the holie Citie of new and true <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> where (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh) the King is verity, Law is Charity, Dignity is Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, Peace Felicity, Life aeternity.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26950:55"/>
            <p>Graunt (deare Father) wee beſeech thee, theſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things neceſſary both for our bodies and ſoules in this life and the next, euen for thy Sonne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> his ſake our Sauiour, to whom with thee and the holy Ghoſt in Trinitie, bee all power, praiſe, glory, thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, and dominion in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity now and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26950:55"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
